All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ע"א, Ayin
Aleph, 71, and we pick up at the משנה mishna on the
top of ע"א. Ayin Aleph. We'd be dealing in the last few
דפים dappim with the whole issue about when do you have to,
if you leave wine with a non-Jew unattended, do you can you
assume, do you need to be concerned that the non-Jew touched the
wine or in other ways handled it, or if you're popping in
and out or he's afraid you'll come back at any time or
any or situation such as that, can you be confident that he
did not touch it, or confident enough anyway so that the wine
would be fine. With this משנה, mishna, we return to some earlier
themes having to do with
getting benefit from the wine
and yeah, what stage is the wine considered
belonging to the non-Jew and when is it considered like it's your
wine and then you're using it and you're getting benefit from it
and so on. So let's take a look at the משנה mishna
and actually a somewhat surprisingly or appropriately, one aspect of this is
going to very much tie in to something חמץ chametz related as
we've also seen issues before about how do you define ביטול, bittul,
is it במשהו? b'mashehu? There was a whole side discussion about חמץ.
chametz. So recognizing that פסח Pesach is just around the corner, we'll
see an interesting חמץ chametz tie-in in a minute as well. All
right, let's start with the משנה. mishna. האומנין שישראל ששלח להם עובדי
כוכבים חבית של יין נסך בשכרן. ha-umanin she-Yisrael she-shalach lahem ovdei kochavim
chavit shel yayin nesech bischaran.
So here you have some Jewish workers and it was time to
get paid and their non-Jewish boss, the owner of the company, said,
"Oh, I don't have any cash on me, but here, take some
wine." So what's their story? By the way, the simple sense here,
I mean this has been an ongoing discussion whether יין נסך yayin
nesech means literally יין נסך yayin nesech or סתם יינם. stam yeinam.
I mean, one would assume by context here he's not דוקא davka
setting them wine that he poured to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Anyway,
one way or another, it's even סתם יינם stam yeinam is אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'ah, you can't get benefit. So here he is, he
sends them this wine. So obviously they can't take it, they can't
get benefit from it. What are they supposed to do? So the
משנה mishna says, מותר לומר לו תן לנו את דמיה. mutar lomar
lo ten lanu et dameha. They can say, "Give us,
no, we don't accept the wine for payment. Give us cash." That
they can do because the wine is not yet theirs, so they're
not selling the wine or benefiting the wine; they're refusing the wine
for payment and they're saying we'd like you to pay us with
cash instead. משיכנס לרשותן אסור. mishenichnas lereshutan assur. Once
however they take possession of the wine, they can't go back and
say, "Actually, we'd like to swap this wine for money." Then it
becomes their wine and then they're actually by giving it back to
the owner and asking for money and instead, they're essentially selling יין
נסך yayin nesech and getting benefit from יין נסך. yayin nesech. Okay,
so that seems pretty straightforward.
Let's see the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב מותר לאדם
לומר לעובד כוכבים צא והפייס עלי מנת המלך. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Rav mutar l'adam lomar l'oved kochavim tzei vehafes alai menat hamelech. Okay,
so we're just so we don't even comment on the משנה, mishna,
we're just going to deal with a similar case, a parallel case.
You owe taxes to the king, so you can say to the
non-Jew, "Would you mind, I don't have cash on me right now,
I don't have anything, would you mind—maybe he's your partner, who knows
what he is—would you mind paying my taxes for me and I'll
reimburse you?" And then if the non-Jew decides to pay the taxes
with wine, it's not your wine, it's not like you asked him
pay the king with wine and therefore you're getting benefit from the
יין נסך. yayin nesech. You said pay the king, he chose to
pay the taxes with wine, but the effect was that he paid
your $10,000 debt and you owe him $10,000. If you remember, we
had this issue
before whereas you tell the storekeeper, "Pay my workers," and if the
storekeeper goes ahead and gives them wine to drink, "Give my workers
food," he gives them wine to drink and then he turns to
you, so he's not turning to you, it's not your wine he
gave them, he's just sending you the bill. Now you owe him
money. Okay, and your relationship to him is just a relationship of
paying a debt. So here too, since you didn't ask to, "Oh,
could you pay off my debt and use your wine to pay
off my debt," then it would be like an extension of you
and like you'd be paying your debt with wine, you just said
pay off my debt and he chose to use wine, so now
he's turning to you, it's just a debt now that you owe
this non-Jew and therefore it's not a problem. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. מתיבי, Mesivei, a challenge you on this. אל
יאמר אדם לעובד כוכבים עמוד תחתי לאוצר. Al yomar adam l'oved kochavim
amod tachtai la-otzar. Don't say to a non-Jew, "Would you please go
ahead and take my place, stand in my stead," for the אוצר.
otzar. רש"י Rashi says אוצר otzar is he wants to read that
meaning also some type of a similar tax collector or an officer
or so on. That you are not allowed to say. So why
not? Why can't you say that and he'll pay it with wine
and even if he pays it with wine, no problem, you didn't
ask him to pay it with wine? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ליה רב, amar lei Rav, so רב Rav said back,
עמוד תחתי לאוצר קאמרת? amod tachtai la-otzar ka-amart? One minute, that's a
different language. There the language you used is not, "Would you mind
please paying my taxes for me?" me? You said, there you said
actually, "take my stead, be in my place." So when you say,
"be in my place," and then he chooses to pay with wine,
this is the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* reads it, then because you
framed it almost as like be my שליח *shaliach*, you know, be
my representative. So therefore when he's choosing to pay with wine, it's
like you're choosing to pay with wine. It's like you're giving the
wine and therefore if the wine is the non-Jew's wine, you're giving
יין נסך yein nesech *yayin nesech* and you're benefiting from יין נסך
yein nesech. *yayin nesech*. So that language he says makes all the
difference. Okay, הלו דמיא *halo damya*, the case רש"י Rashi *Rashi* that
I'm talking about is similar to the other case in the ברייתא
braita. *Braita*. אלא הא *ela ha*, אבל אמר amar, מצילני מן האוצר
*aval amar matzileni min ha-otzar*, you can say, "Please save me," you
know, "please save me from the tax collector." That you're allowed to
say. Okay, at you'd take, can you please, you know, pay my
taxes for me? I'll reimburse you. Could you please save me from
the tax collector? And then if the non-Jew chooses to pay wine,
that's the non-Jew's choice. And when he comes to you, he's just
coming to you with a bill. Okay, but if you say a
language that's very much a שליח *shaliach* language, "be in my stead"
regarding the taxes, okay, then there, then when he pays with wine,
it's much more like you're paying with wine. That's the way רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* reads it. תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*, I should say, is a
little bit, feels like even if you say that language, if it's
totally the non-Jew, if basically all you owe is cash, you have
a $10,000 tax bill, and then even if you say the language
of "be in my stead," at the end of the day, right,
he's paying a debt of $10,000, and even if he's using wine,
it shouldn't matter. So if you look at תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*, תוספות
Tosfos. *Tosafot* actually says that even the problematic case is a much
narrower case. תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* says אמר אמימר Amar Ameimar: *amar Amemar*,
I'm sorry, not that one. הלו דמיא לסיפא אבל אמר מצילני מן
האוצר *halo damya leseiifa aval amar matzileni min ha-otzar*, okay. So פירוש
רש"י Rashi משום רבי יחיאל דכי אמר ליה amar lei, הכי מותר
משום דמצי לסלוקי בזוזי מן האוצר ואם כן כי נמי יהיב בי
כוכביא יין לאו צערא דנפשיה דישראל קא עביד ומשום הכי הרי זה
שרי כהאי גוונא *peirush Rashi mishum Rabi Yechiel deki amar lei hachi
mutar mishum dematzi lesalokei bezuzei min ha-otzar veim kein ki nami yahiv
bei kochvaya yayin lav tzara denafshia deYisrael ka avid umishum hachi harei
zeh shari kehai gavna*. Fine. Then he paid, could have paid with
money, if he paid with wine, that was his business. וכי אמר
ליה amar lei אות תחתיי משמע הלשון הוי תחתיי במקומי *veki amar
lei ot tachtai mashma halashon hevei tachtai bimkomi*, like "play my role."
וכל מאי דיהיב כאילו יהיב ישראל דמי דהא במקומו הוא כן פירש
הקונטרס *vechol mai deyahiv keilu yahiv Yisrael dami deha bimkomo hu kein
peirush ha-Kuntres*. So then even if, you know, he could have paid
money and the non-Jew chose to pay wine, once if you framed
it like "you are my representative, do this in my stead," it's
like you're paying with wine even though it was the non-Jew's choice.
That's the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* reads it. And the תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafot* continues saying, we're in the middle of the תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*,
הלו דמיא *halo damya*. So this says ולא נראה *velo nireh*. That
does not appear correct. דאם כן פשיטא דמצילני מן האוצר דשרי כיון
דמרי דיכול לסלקו *deim kein pshita dematzileni min ha-otzar deshari keivan demarei
diyachol lesalko*. This says then the whole thing would be first of
all like it's a stretch to say that case is a problem
and then it would be obvious that when you just said "save
me" it would be permissible. לכן נראה לי שישראל חייב למלך יין
*lachen nireh li sheYisrael chayav lamelech yayin*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* wants to
say we're talking in a bigger חידוש chiddush *chiddush*. Actually you owe
wine to the king. Okay, it's not like a $10,000
taxes, it's like you owe a percentage of your, you know, annual
produce to the king. So if you're in the wine business, you
owe 10% of that to the king. You owe the king wine.
Okay, now, and therefore if you say "be in my stead" where
I owe the king wine, "pay wine to the king for my
debt of wine," so that and you're the non-Jew are going to
pay the king with your, with your wine which is forbidden, then
it's a debt of wine, you're paying with wine, then it's really
like I am using your wine to pay my debt and it's
a problem of יין נסך yayin nesech *yayin nesech*. Okay, so that
all makes a lot of sense, but then there's a tremendous חידוש
*chiddush* now in תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot*. Even though my debt is wine
and the non-Jew is paying wine for me, if I slightly frame
it in a different way, "save me from my debt," that gets,
that allows it. Okay. So he says מכל מקום שרי כי אמר
ליה מצילני מן האוצר משום דמשמע הכי קאמר ליה סלק אותו במה
שתוכל *mikol makom shari ki amar lei matzileni min ha-otzar mishum demashma
hachi ka-amar lei salek oto be-mah she-tuchal*. Then I'm like basically saying,
look, I know I owe the king wine, but do whatever you
have you can do to get me out of my debt. Bribe
him maybe, maybe get him to pay cash, maybe pay cash instead
of wine. If you wind up paying wine, that's also good. Okay.
So therefore it's, so according to תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot*, it's a big
חידוש *chiddush*, right? According to רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*, let me just step
back and say it again. According to רש"י *Rashi*, the case in
the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* and the case in the ברייתא *Braita* is
you owe cash. Okay, and you owe cash, you ask the non-Jew
to pay for you, you'd reimburse the non-Jew. So you know in
the end of the day, you're not paying wine, if the non-Jew
chooses to pay wine, your debt was cash, anything he paid with,
that's just his choice of what to pay this $10,000 debt with
at the end of the day, you just owe the non-Jew for
the debt of the value of what he paid but you're not
using the wine. Even if that's true that you just owe cash
and the non-Jew is making his own choices about what to pay
with, you know, if you frame it as "be my representative, be
in my stead, אות תחתיי *ot tachtai*," then and the non-Jew pays
wine, it's like you paid wine. So for רש"י *Rashi*, even though
the debt is cash and the non-Jew is making his own choices.
making his own choice if you frame it in a particular way
it makes it like you paid wine. So that's a חומרא. תוספות
Tosafos makes a much more lenient conclusion. תוספות Tosafos, says if the
debt could be a debt of wine and even if the debt
is a debt of wine and the non-Jew is paying wine it'll
be okay it's not like you paid wine as long as you
framed it to the non-Jew not directly pay my debt then it
means pay wine and you're paying wine for me but as long
as you framed it as like something like get me out of
it try to do whatever you can to get me out of
my debt okay that's enough of a distancing that it means that
even if in the end he pays wine it's not like you
paid wine. Okay so interesting debates of רש"י and תוספות. Tosafos, You
might remember that this goes back for that discussion earlier like when
you say to the storekeeper pay my workers and the storekeeper pays
them in wine and then he comes back to you the example
I gave in a case of like you say to somebody like
you say to your employees go ahead and order whatever
you want and then I'll reimburse you or you say to somebody
on the street like go into the restaurant poor person who's asking
for money go order what you want I'll pay it off and
they order like בשר בחלב basar bechalav which is אסור בהנאה assur
behana'ah is it like you are benefiting from the בשר בחלב basar
bechalav or no they're doing their transaction and now you just owe
the storekeeper money. Okay so this is very much a continuation of
that. According to רש"י it's not so much of a חידוש because
it was just a debt of money to begin with. But תוספות
Tosafot reads it that it could even be a case of a
debt of wine being paid with wine and framed the right way
it's not like you were paying the wine you just owe the
non-Jew the money and the non-Jew did whatever the non-Jew did. Okay
so now we take a look at the next משנה. mishna
So that was a continuation that was like going back to that
issue about when is it that it's
like you were paying using the wine and when was it that
no they did what they did and you just owe the money.
Now המוכר יינו לעובד
כוכבים. Hamocher yeino l'oved kochavim. Now we're gonna get a case not
where it's the non-Jew's wine it's your wine but you're selling it
to the non-Jew. So what you got to do in this case
is you have to make sure that the non-Jew doesn't handle it
before the sale is final because if the non-Jew handles it before
the sale is final it becomes יין נסך yayin nesech. and now
you're selling you can't sell him יין נסך. yayin nesech So you
have to sell it to him and the sale has to be
final before he gets a chance to handle it. So let's see
how what the משנה Mishnah says and this is going to get
us into a question which is when does a transaction between a
Jew and a non-Jew when does that sale become final? Okay so
המוכר יינו לעובדי כוכבים. Hamocher yeino l'ovdei kochavim. You're selling your wine
to the non-Jew. פסק עד שלא מדד דמיו מותרין. Pasak ad shelo
madad damav mutarin. If you basically fixed the price okay and before
you measured it out all right then before then the money is
permissible. Okay so מדד madad now the question is why okay so
the easy way to understand this because it doesn't mention when the
money changed hands it just mentions when the price was fixed. Okay
so the simple sense of this is we're not dealing with money
changing hands money is not what finalizes a transaction with the non-Jew.
משיכה Meshicha the normal things that finalize a transaction between Jew and
Jew would finalize a transaction between Jew and non-Jew okay which would
be משיכה meshicha הגבהה hagbah those types of things. The only thing
is is that if the price isn't yet fixed there's not yet
enough גמר דעת g'mar da'as right if I'm measuring it out but
I don't yet know how much I'm paying I mean this happens
to me sometimes you go to the cash register ready to pay
and you say wait what how much was that a pound oh
whatever no forget it I'm not buying that.
Okay so sometimes even after you ring it up you say wait
I thought it was whatever no take that off. So anyway so
if it's עד שלא מדד ad shelo madad the משיכה meshicha isn't
yet קונה. koneh. The משיכה meshicha is only קונה koneh once the
price was fixed. Okay so if the price is fixed and then
you measured it into the vessel of the non-Jew you poured the
wine into the non-Jew's pitcher whatever it was then דמיו מותרין damav
mutarin then it's a good sale and you can keep the money
because as soon as the money goes into the non-Jew's pitcher the
sale is final and the non-Jew doesn't handle it until after it
went into his pitcher so it only becomes forbidden wine after the
sale is final. But מדד עד שלא פסק madad ad shelo pasak
if first you measured it and you poured it into the non-Jew's
pitcher and you haven't yet fixed the price now you got a
problem because now the non-Jew has wine in his pitcher which you
still own because the price hasn't been fixed yet and now we're
afraid he's going to touch it or whatever and it'll be סתם
יינם stam yeinam and now when you say oh how much is
it oh it's a dollar an ounce or whatever it is at
that moment that's when the sale becomes final but at that moment
it's already forbidden. It's your until then it's your wine which became
סתם יינם stam yeinam which you can't sell to the non-Jew. Okay
so in that case מדד עד שלא פסק דמיו אסורין madad ad
shelo pasak damav asurin the money is forbidden. All right so you
get the idea you need the sale to be final before he
has a chance to handle it. So as long as the sale
is final when it goes into his vessel that's a second before
he has a chance to access the vessel right then you're safe.
But if when it goes into his vessel the sale isn't yet
final Then it's a problem because then it's still your wine, now
he can touch it, and now it's forbidden and now you can't
finalize the sale. All right, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר אמימר:
משיכה בעובד כוכבים קנה. meshicha be'oved kochavim koneh. Drawing something, an act
of משיכה meshicha similarly to an act of being in his vessel,
all the normal types of קניינים kinyanim that have to do with
a physical control over or mastery over the object that you are
taking possession of. That's like משיכה, meshicha, חצר, chatzer, כלי, kli, all
those types of things. That's implied by the word משיכה. meshicha. So
משיכה, meshicha, those types of taking physical possession of the object, that
works when you're selling something to a non-Jew. Okay, and that's the
simple read of our משנה Mishnah because our משנה Mishnah, didn't mention
any exchange of money. תדע, Teda, and I'll prove it to you,
דהני פרסאי, dehanei parsaye, these Persians, משדרי פרדשני להדדי meshadderei pardashnei lehadadei
when they send gifts to one another, it either means gifts or
it could mean that basically רש"י says when they send a sampling,
they've done a sale in the store and they send a sample
of it to be tasted, okay, before they deliver the rest of
the products, ולא הדרי בהו, velo hadrei behu, and then they don't
reverse it. Once, so either if this means once a gift is
given and the other side takes possession, they don't feel that they
can back out of giving the gift, okay, although that might just
be a politeness thing. Okay, or the other read of רש"י is
once they send a sample and the guy takes possession of the
sample and he likes the sample, it's a sale, then they know
that the sale is final once you take possession okay at that
moment the sale is final when they do משיכה. meshicha. So תוספות
Tosefos says, you know, this isn't exactly a proof, right, what how
Persians among themselves, what in their דינא דמלכותא, dina demalchuta, what conventions
they go by, doesn't prove necessarily what הלכה Halacha recognizes as final.
But you know, it's like a small support, okay. Look, this is
the way they practice and anyway משיכה meshicha works by non-Jews. Okay,
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says לעולם
אימא לך משיכה בעובד כוכבים אינו קונה. le'olam eima lach meshicha be'oved
kochavim eino koneh. No, I can claim, or תוספות Tosefos says is
it I can claim or that I really I really assert that
משיכה meshicha is not doesn't work by non-Jews. והאי דלא הדרי בהו,
vehai dela hadrei behu, so how about the fact that by their
conventions they don't return things after they take physical possession of the
object? דרמא סרוכא הוא דנקיט להו. derama sarucha hu denakit lehu. That's
just a certain degree of like, I don't know, arrogance—I don't know
if you'd call it arrogance—but I would say like politeness, okay. It's
a certain way of like a דרך ארץ derech eretz that they
do that they don't return it after that point, but it doesn't
mean that that is when it legally is binding. So normally the
alternative of משיכה, meshicha, which as again said suggests all the types
of קניינים kinyanim that are the physical taking of possession of the
object, the alternative to that is כסף, kesef, the paying of the
money. So
רב אשי Rav Ashi is saying I don't buy into the idea
that it's קניין—it's kinyan משיכה—I meshicha say taking of possession is only
through כסף. kesef. This is a major debate, primarily in the גמרא
Gemara in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and
ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. Which קניין kinyan works according to the תורה
Torah for Jews? One says כסף kesef and the other says משיכה.
meshicha. Okay, we all agree that דרבנן derabbanan what works for Jews
is not כסף, kesef, it's the physical taking possession of the object—משיכה,
meshicha, הגבהה, hagbahah, חצר, chatzer, and so on. But is that the
way it is in the תורה Torah or did the תורה Torah
actually have it being כסף kesef and the rabbis negated that for
whatever various reasons and they said it's going to be משיכה? meshicha?
So that's a debate in terms of Jews, but the but the
also implication of that, or what the גמרא Gemara sort of spells
out in there is
that whatever you say works by Jews, it's the opposite by non-Jews.
So if by Jews according to the תורה Torah it's משיכה, meshicha,
by non-Jews it's כסף. kesef. If for Jews according to the תורה
Torah it's כסף, kesef, for non-Jews it's משיכה. meshicha. So this debate
which קניין kinyan works for non-Jews is a big debate in the
גמרא. Gemara. It also has huge implications for something that's coming up
in the next few days, which is what big sale to a
non-Jew is coming up in the next few days? מכירת חמץ. mechirahs
chametz. How do you do the מכירת חמץ, mechirahs chametz, how do
we פסקן pasken about which קניין kinyan works for a non-Jew? So
when they do the מכירת חמץ mechirahs chametz to a non-Jew, they
basically do like every type of קניין kinyan under the sun. First
of all, you get him to pay money, that's כסף. kesef. You
get him to do an act of משיכה, meshicha, you do חליפין,
chalipin, you do חצר, chatzer, you do
like—whatever, דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina demalchuta dina, you do twenty different קניינים.
kinyanim. Okay, but that is basically to cover your bases because it's
not clear in the end what the מסקנא maskana of this גמרא
Gemara is. So if you look, this huge תוספות רב אשי אומר,
Tosafos Rav Ashi Omer, תוספות Tosafot tries to figure out what is
our פסק psak about קניינים kinyanim about non-Jews? And for תוספות, the
big question is not חמץ בפסח, chametz bePesach, but because that hadn't
become as universal yet, the big question is selling a piece of
an animal that was about to have a baby. Because how do
you get out of בכור bechor nowadays? The הלכות halachos of בכור
bechor still apply. And the way you get out of בכור bechor
is if the non-Jew has a slight ownership in the mother, there's
no הלכה halacha of בכור bechor of the child. So they would
sell the ear of all of their female, you know, sheep and
cows or whatever to non-Jews. Okay, so what קניין kinyan do you
have to do to sell it? So if you look at the
end of this תוספות, this big תוספות רב אשי, Tosafos Rav Ashi,
תוספות says... so like this, he says,
you see where there's an asterisk? It's about twelve lines from the
bottom, it's near where on the right-hand side there's a bracket and
ועוד עיין תוספות יבמות. ve'od ayein Tosafos Yevamos. So if you go
in about four words there's an asterisk where it says, והרוצה לחוש
לדברי רש"י ורבנו תם, veharotze lachush ledivrei Rashi veRabbeinu Tam, because Rashi
and Rabbeinu Tam debate what the פסק psak is, is the פסק
psak כסף kessef or משיכה meshikha by a non-Jew? So if you
want to be play it safe, המקנה בהמה לעובד כוכבים לפטורה מן
הבכורה, hamakne behema le'oved kokhavim lepotrah min habekhorah, if you are selling
a piece of an animal to a non-Jew to get out of
the laws of בכור, bekhor, צריך שיתן עובד כוכבים כסף וגם משיכת
עובד כוכבים בסימטא או לרשותו של עובד כוכבים שיהא לו, tzarikh sheyiten
oved kokhavim kessef vegam meshikhat oved kokhavim besimta o lereshuto shel oved
kokhavim sheyehe lo, because you have to get the non-Jew to both
pay a little money and you have to get him to do
a משיכה, meshikha, draw the animal. Now משיכה meshikha doesn't work in
a public domain, משיכה meshikha only works on like in a side
alley or משיכה meshikha into his actual domain itself. And let's say
the non-Jew doesn't have his own domain, I don't know why, and
you can't find a side alley that's considered a non-public domain, ואם
אין לו רשות עובד כוכבים, ve'im ein lo reshus oved kokhavim, so
look, it's already like this idea of doing all these crazy manipulations
to do these pseudo-sales already started in תוספות, מקנה לו ישראל חדר
בביתו ועובד כוכבים ינעול ויפתח, makne lo Yisrael cheder beveito ve'oved kokhavim
yin'ol veyiftach, so first you gotta do two steps. First I gotta
sell you the non-Jew a room in my house, go do a
קנין kinyan on that room, okay, ובהכי קני ליה לרשות, ubehakhei kani
leh lereshus, that's a קנין kinyan on on, you know, on a
physical property, you know, on like real estate, ואחר כך ימשוך עובד
כוכבים הבהמה לאותו חדר. ve'achar kakh yimshokh oved kokhavim habehema le'oso cheder.
ובבכורות פליגי אמוראי מה צריך שיקנה עובד
כוכבים מן הבהמה. ubevkhoros peligi amora'ei mah tzarikh sheyikne oved kokhavim min
habehema. Okay, so that's number one, so you gotta do כסף kessef
and חצר chatzer or כסף kessef and משיכה. meshikha. Now he goes
on, how much of the animal does he have to own? This
is already off top- even more
off topic. ובבכורות פרק קמא פליגי אמוראי מה צריך שיקנה עובד כוכבים
מן הבהמה, ubevkhoros perek kama peligi amora'ei mah tzarikh sheyikne oved kokhavim
min habehema, איכא מן דאמר שצריך שיקנה דבר שעושה אותה טרפה, ika
man de'amar shetzarikh sheyikne davar she'oseh osah tereifa, he has to own
enough of the animal that would turn it into a טרפה tereifa
if it was removed. ואיכא מן דאמר אפילו אזנו, ve'ika man de'amar
afilu ozno, even the ear. ונראה להחמיר להקנות לעובד כוכבים דבר שעושה
אותה טרפה, venireh lehachmir lehaknos le'oved kokhavim davar she'oseh osah tereifa, you
should be מחמיר. machmir. כגון הריאה, kegon hare'ah, sell him the lungs,
והראש מן הבהמה veharosh min habehema or the head. Of course those
things have real value. Okay, או מן העובר, o min ha'ubar, or
sell him a little piece of the fetus, כשהיא מעוברת keshehi me'uberes
etc. etc. Okay. And then he- and then he says, but you
don't have to pay- I should read the next line because it's
similar to מכירת חמץ. mekhiras chametz. Even as- although we're doing כסף,
kessef, it's enough to pay a- to pay a symbolic amount of
money. He doesn't have to give the amount of money that the
thing is actually worth. Okay, which is like what we do, we
don't get the non-Jew to pay a hundred thousand dollars or whatever
it is. אומנם אין צריך שיתן עובד כוכבים מעות שווה הראש והריאה,
omnam ein tzarikh sheyiten oved kokhavim ma'os shoveh harosh vehare'ah, you don't
have to pay the amount, the actual value of the head or
the lungs, אלא סגי שיקנה בפרוטה, ela sagi sheyikne beprouta, just give
a פרוטה, prouta, ואף על פי שיותר היא כפליים, ve'af al pi
sheyoser hi kiflayim, even though it's worth many, many times as much.
אפילו הכי אין לחוש משום ביטול מקח, afilu hakhei ein lachush mishum
bitul mekach, oh, it's not serious, you only gave a dollar. דאנן
סהדי שישראל גמר ואקני לעובד כוכבים כדי להיפטר מן הבכורה. de'anan sahadei
sheYisrael gamar ve'aknei le'oved kokhavim kedei lehipater min habekhorah. We know that
even though the Jew is only getting a dollar, he really wants
the non-Jew to own the lungs in order to get out of
the הלכה halacha of בכור. bekhor. Okay, so here you go, I
just thought it was so appropriate, we're in the season of מכירת
חמץ, mekhiras chametz, and all this like, you know, הערמה ha'arama and
this pseudo-sale, you know, and you do all these other things, you
don't pay the full amount, but you do all these קניינים kinyanim
in order to go ahead and to sell it, which just- which-
which- which- which now I just have to tell the joke that
I love, which is, so
a Reform, Conservative, and Orthodox rabbi get together and they decide, we
gotta come up with some הלכה halacha we can all agree upon,
okay, something that we all agree like, you know, is- so- so
they say, ah, here, let's- let's all agree that we think that
it's אסור assur to smoke, you know, because that's a health hazard,
we can all understand that even from a purely humanistic perspective or
whatever, you know, that we shouldn't be allowed to smoke or whatever.
So fine, they all פסקן, pasken, they come out with a פסק,
psak, it's אסור assur to smoke. Okay, a month later they all
bump into each other on the street and they're all smoking cigarettes.
So they say, what do you mean, I thought we all came
to this פסק? psak? So they turn to the Reform rabbi and
he says, well, it's true, but you know at the end of
the day I think the key is really people making autonomous decisions
and therefore, you know, that's- therefore even though that was our decision,
everybody should be, you know, should have that freedom. So they turn
to the Conservative rabbi, they say, what's your story? He said, well,
yeah, but you know if you looked at the historical context of
our original ruling and, you know, you read all of the various
manuscripts and the records or whatever, there's enough room to say that
it's allowed. So they turn to the Orthodox rabbi, they say, okay,
but what's your excuse? So he says, I don't know why you're
giving me a hard time, I sold my lungs to a non-Jew!
So- alright, so there you
go, right in תוספות, selling the lungs. Alright, anyway, moving back to
the
גמרא. Gemara. Alright, back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, now
אמר רב אשי מנא אמינא לה, amar Rav Ashi mana amina lah,
how do I- says Rav Ashi, where do I get this idea
from that it goes by כסף kessef and it does not go
by משיכה meshikha okay, for a non-Jew? And again the משנה, Mishnah
the simple read of the משנה Mishnah. is משיכה, meshikha, there's no
כסף kessef mentioned in the משנה. Mishnah רב אשי Rav Ashi says,
where do I get this from? מי דאמר להו רב להנהו סבוייתא
סבוייתא, Mi de'amar lehu Rav lehanu savuyata savuyata, רב Rav said to
these wine sellers, כי חייליתו חמרא לעובדי כוכבים ki haylitu chamra l'ovdei
kochavim
when you are basically measuring out wine to the non-Jews, שקלו זוזי
מינייהו, shaklu zuzei mineihu,
get them to pay the money first, והדר חיילו להו, vehadar haylu
lehu, and then measure out the wine. So get the money upfront.
So רב Rav emphasizes money. So the פשט pshat reading of רב
Rav is that money finalizes the sale. Then be my guest, sell
them whatever you're going to sell them, they already own their wine,
you're not concerned that they'll handle it. Okay, ואי לא נקיטי בהדייהו
זוזי, ve'i lo nekitei behadeihu zuzei,
now let's say they don't have any cash on them, what are
you supposed to do? Here's the solution. They don't have cash on
them, here's what I want you to do. Okay,
אוזפינהו, ozfinhu, lend them the money they need for the sale. In
the end of the day, it's going to be on credit anyway.
But what you'll, the way you make it on credit is, give
them the 20 bucks, have them give you the 20 bucks back.
Now they bought it with כסף, kessef, and now they owe you
20 bucks rather than just saying you're buying it on credit. Have
them actually pay the cash by you lending them the cash. Okay.
So, אוזפינהו, ozfinhu, so first lend them the money, והדר שקילו מינייהו,
vehadar shekilu mineihu, then take the cash from them, כי היכי דלהוי
הלואה גבייהו, ki heichi d'lehavei halva'ah gabeihu, so that it's just they
just owe you the money but they've actually paid in cash. דאי
לא עבדיתו הכי, de'i lo avditu hachi, if you don't do this,
if they take possession without taking the money, so כי קא הוי
יין נסך ברשותייכו קא הוי, ki ka havei yayin nesech birshuteichu ka
havei, when they get now take physical possession the sale isn't final,
it becomes יין נסך yayin nesech while it's still your
wine, וכי שקליתו דמי יין נסך קא שקליתו, vechi sheklitu dmei yayin
nesech ka sheklitu, you're taking the money of יין נסך. yayin nesech
Very clear explanation. It's almost explicit that it's the money that finalizes
the transaction, right? So it's very clear whatever the פשט pshat of
the משנה Mishnah, is, it seems very clear that רב Rav at
least is of the position that money with non-Jews is what finalizes
the transaction. That's a pretty good support to רב אשי's Rav Ashi
position. ואי סלקא דעתך משיכה בעובדי כוכבים קונה, ve'i salka daitach meshicha
b'ovdei kochavim koneh, and if you think that what you need is
the physical possession of the object,
so מידי דמשכה עובדי כוכבים קנייה, midei demashcha ovdei kochavim kanyei, so
he says I don't understand why you need to pay the money
upfront. Who needs to pay the money? As soon from the moment
they draw the wine to them or it's in their vessel, at
that second they own it. יין נסך לא הוי עד דנגע ביה,
yayin nesech lo havei ad denaga beih, it won't become יין נסך
yayin nesech until they touch it or they have an opportunity to
touch it, which is a second later than they take physical possession.
So why is רב Rav so worried that the money be paid?
As long as משיכה's קונה meshicha koneh. like we read our משנה,
mishna if the price is set and משיכה's קונה, meshikha koneh they
own it but a second before they have an opportunity to make
it forbidden just by physical taking of possession. Why does רב Rav
care about the money? So that's a very good point. רב Rav
clearly seems to be feeling physical possession does not work, it's the
money that makes it final. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like,
so the גמרא Gemara has an answer to this. אי דקא חייל
ורמי למנא דישראל, ei deka hayel verami l'mana d'Yisrael, if they're pouring
the wine into a Jew's flask, הכי נמי, hachi nami, you'd be
right, you wouldn't have to pay the money, I could you know,
and it just the physical drawing of the wine to them would
finalize the sale before they had a second before they had a
moment to touch it. לא צריכא דקא חייל ורמי למנא דעובדי כוכבים,
lo tzricha deka hayel verami l'mana d'ovdei kochavim, you need it that
you're pouring into the vessel of a non-Jew. Now big deal, that
all the more reason he should own it the minute it hits
the vessel, if it's his vessel. Ah, but here's the problem. The
problem is in the non-Jew's wine flask is a little leftover wine
from the last time he used it, okay? So what you're doing
here is,
here he is in the store, right with his with his bottle,
his wine flask. Here you are, you're pouring this wine from the
barrel right into the wine flask, but there's a little bit of
drops down here. Okay. So it's going to you're going to he's
going to take possession, it's true he doesn't have at this moment
he can't touch it. Okay. And we assume he can't touch it
and he'll take possession from the time it hits the bottle. And
then it'll be his before he has a chance to touch it.
But when it's hitting the bottle, it's mixing with those drops of
wine that's forbidden, okay? And יין נסך yayin nesech is אסור במשהו,
assur b'mashahu,
so at the moment it is becoming יין נסך yayin nesech. sort
of at the moment if you want to say a millisecond because
the wine hits the drops maybe before it hits the bottom of
the vessel, okay, it's becoming יין נסך yayin nesech a millisecond before
he owns it or at the same time that he's owning it.
Okay and then it's a problem, then it's like your יין נסך
yayin nesech that you're selling to him because because he needs to
own it before it becomes יין נסך. yayin nesech So that's the
problem, okay. And that's why רב Rav said the way you get
out of this is you have him pay upfront, then he owns
it before you poured it. So the response is and the way
this is the way תוספות reads first response, you're right from that
teaching of רב Rav it sounds like money finalizes the sale, because
רב Rav says have pay up front and you'll solve the problem.
But that doesn't mean that money is the only way a non-Jew
can take possession. A non-Jew can also take possession by משיכה. meshicha
If that's true, why is this a problem if even if he
hasn't paid the money, doesn't he own it before he can touch
it? And the answer is no. If he hasn't paid the money,
this is a problem because he it becomes יין נסך yayin nesech.
before he owns it. We could say you have both options of
taking possession, money and משיכה, meshicha but in this case, it's יין
נסך yayin nesech. before he owns it because when it hits those
drops before it hits the bottom of the vessel, it's already a
problem. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, וכי תימא
ורמי למאן דאמר דעובד כוכבים. vechi teima verami lamand'amar d'oveid kochavim. So
the גמרא Gemara says, סוף סוף כי מטא לאוירא דמנא קנייה יין
נסך לא הוי עד דמטי לארעא דמנא. sof sof ki mata l'avira
demana kanyei, yayin nesech lo havei ad demati l'ara demana. Okay,
so I said it only becomes he only owns it when it
hits the bottom of the vessel, but the גמרא Gemara says it's
not true. Once it enters the airspace of the vessel, that's קנין
כלי. kinyan kli. Okay, so קנין כלי kinyan kli works in the
airspace. So it's his and it only becomes if משיכה meshikha. were
to be קונה koneh this shouldn't be a problem because it would
be his and here and it only becomes יין נסך when it
gets to the bottom. שמע מינה ניצוק חיבור, shema mina nitzok chibbur,
should we therefore conclude if this is a problem that ניצוק חיבור,
nitzok chibbur, that something is connected by being poured? Meaning what? At
the moment this hits the bottom of the vessel, which wine is
forbidden? Just the wine that's mixed up with those drops, or because
this wine at the bottom is forbidden, all of this wine at
the top is forbidden as well? That's ניצוק חיבור. nitzok chibbur. It's
all considered one unit. So the גמרא Gemara says, I could explain,
assuming that משיכה meshikha, and כלי kli is קונה koneh, and the
question is, if משיכה meshikha and כלי kli is קונה, koneh why
doesn't he take possession here before it's a problem, and your answer
is because there's some wine at the bottom, but then the question
is, but that but this wine should still he should still be
קונה, koneh but I could explain that the reason he's not קונה
koneh, this wine before it becomes a problem is because it's all
connected to the drops at the bottom, ניצוק חיבור. nitzok chibbur. So
that could be your explanation about why this would be a problem,
but we don't want to be forced to conclude ניצוק חיבור. nitzok
chibbur. We want to leave that as an open question. It's not
clear how we rule about that question. So the only way you'll
be able to explain why this is a problem is if you
say ניצוק חיבור, nitzok chibbur, but do we really want to be
forced to say that? So שמע מינה ניצוק חיבור, shema mina nitzok
chibbur, should we therefore have to conclude that ניצוק nitzok that poured
is a connection? לא, lo,
no, not necessarily. I'll give you another way to explain why this
would be a problem. Okay, אידי דנקיט ליה עובד כוכבים לכלי בידיה
הכא נמי. eidei d'nakat lei oveid kochavim l'kli b'yadei hacha nami.
You're right, if he was holding onto the vessel, then the only
way to explain why it would be a problem before he would
be קונה koneh, it would be the principle of ניצוק חיבור, nitzok
chibbur, it's all connected by the pouring. לא צריכא lo tzerichan our
case we need it דמנח אארעא. demanach a'ara. Okay, so here's the
question. You're assuming why does this work, I mean I think I
jumped the gun a little bit. Why your question that he should
be קונה koneh it in the airspace, it's not yet the issue
of a קנין כלי. kinyan kli. I jumped ahead a little. The
גמרא Gemara gets to that. At this stage it's a קנין kinyan
of הגבהה. hagbah. He's holding onto, let me pick up my hand,
he's holding onto the vessel, and therefore he's keeping the wine off
of the ground. He's being מגביה magbi'ah the wine. The wine is
suspended because he's holding onto it. Okay, so that's why we assumed
it worked because of הגבהה, hagbah, although I must tell you I
don't exactly get why we were assuming in the airspace it works
because of הגבהה, hagbah, because then it's in the airspace of something
I'm holding but I'm not supporting the wine until it hits the
bottom. But anyway the גמרא Gemara says your assumption that this should
be קונה koneh when it gets to the airspace and therefore you
say so then it should be okay, okay, that would be true
if he's holding onto it. But in our case he's not holding
onto it. Here it is, it's on the counter. Okay, so his
vessel is on the
counter. And in that case he's not קונה koneh in the airspace.
Okay, and that's why presumably he's only going to be קונה koneh
when it hits the bottom and therefore it's already going to be
יין נסך. And that's why this is a problem. He won't be
able to take possession before it becomes a problem. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says if he was holding onto it
you'd be right that he should be able to take possession and
save it from being a problem. לא צריכא lo tzericha you'd need
it דמנח אארעא. demanach a'ara. Okay, that it's on the ground. And
since it's on the ground he only takes possession when it hits
the bottom. And therefore at that stage it's already even without saying
ניצוק חיבור, nitzok chibbur, possession of it is only at the bottom
of the vessel, and at that stage it's mixing with the drops
of wine and it's already a problem of יין נסך. So that's
why רב Rav said you had to pay the money first. If
you didn't pay the money first, even if we were to assume
that משיכה meshikha were to also work by a non-Jew, he would
not take possession early enough because possession would only happen when it
hits the bottom and when it hits the bottom it's already
a problem. Okay, anyway. All right, so the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* says like this. That's how we explain why you
have to pay the money upfront. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says ותקני ליה כליו *v'tikni lei keilav*, okay? So, so what, says
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, why is
that
it's still not taking possession because of the כלי *kli*? And presumably,
even if he's not holding it and even if it's not הגבהה
hagba'ah, *hagbaah*, let it work through קנין kinyan. כלי *kinyan kli*. So
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says שמעת מינה *Shmas mina*, should we hear
from this, כליו של לוקח ברשות מוכר לא קנה לוקח *keilo shel
lokei’ach birshut mocher lo kana lokei’ach*, that the reason it doesn't work
by a קנין kinyan כלי *kinyan kli* is maybe because you're in
the Jew's store. So that's a debate: if I put stuff in
my bag and I'm in your, and I'm in your domain, does
my, does it being in my bag take possession? Okay, that's a
general question of קנין kinyan, כלי *kinyan kli*. כלי *kli* will work
if we're in neither of our domains, if we're in like a
side street, then it's in my bag, I take possession, or in
my pitcher. But what about if we're in a, your domain? You're
the seller. So since it's fundamentally your store, just 'cause it's in
my bag doesn't yet mean that I own it, maybe. Does קנין
kinyan כלי *kinyan kli* work? So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is saying,
and maybe what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is suggesting here is, maybe
we can even forget about the drops at the bottom. Okay? The
point is, even if משיכה meshikha *meshicha* works, the reason that this,
he doesn't take possession yet is because he's not holding onto it,
so it's not הגבהה *hagbaah*. It's, it's a כלי *kli* in the
seller's domain, so it doesn't work קנין kinyan, כלי *kinyan kli*. So
you get this scenario: he comes, he puts his pitcher down. The
guy pours the wine in. He's not holding the pitcher, it's not
הגבהה *hagbaah*. He's not, it's a, his כלי *kli* in the guy's
store, it's not a קנין kinyan כלי *kinyan kli*. So maybe we
can even forget about, you know, the drops of wine or something,
and we could say that it doesn't work because he doesn't take
possession yet and now he has access to touch it before he's
been able to do a קנין *kinyan* on it. Okay, so that
could be the explanation. רב *Rav* says pay the money first because
money will work. Does that prove that משיכה meshikha *meshicha* doesn't work?
No, maybe משיכה meshicha *meshicha* does work and he just hasn't taken
possession yet. There's no הגבהה *hagbaah*, there's no כלי *kli*, and that's
why, and that's why it's going to become יין נסך *yayin nesech*
before he takes possession. Okay, but the גמרא *Gemara* says, but that'll
only work if you say קנין כלי *kinyan kli* doesn't work in
the seller's domain. Do we really want to conclude that way? שמעת
מינה *Shmas mina*, should we conclude from this, כליו של לוקח ברשות
מוכר לא קנה *keilo shel lokei’ach birshut mocher lo kana*, that the
vessels of the purchaser don't work with a קנין כלי *kinyan kli*
in the seller's domain, 'cause that's how you'll explain that he's not
קונה koneh *koneh* yet? לא קנה לוקח *lo kana lokei’ach*. לא *Lo*,
no, you don't have to come to that conclusion. לא למימרא לך
קנה לוקח *Lo l'meima lach kana lokei’ach*, and I could tell you
in general קנין כלי *kinyan kli* would work even in the seller's
domain. והכא במאי עסקינן כגון דאיכא עכבת יין אפומא דכווזנתא *V'hacha b'mai
askinan, kegon d'ika akavas yayin apuma d'kuznasa*. There is some holding back
of the wine on the lip of the vessel, okay? דקמא קמא
אינסוכי *d'kama kama insichlei*. Okay, and the, and every little bit first
becomes a problem. So what we're basically doing is, we're saying it's
a variation of what we said before. Maybe he would be קונה
koneh קנין כלי *koneh kinyan kli*. So our question is, if he's
קונה koneh. קנין כלי *koneh kinyan kli*, right, then maybe he should
be קונה koneh *koneh* the minute it hits the airspace, and then
he owns it before it becomes and mixes with those drops of
wine on the bottom. So what we're saying now is no, here's
the story: there's like a lip to this, and there is some
drops of wine, of the wine from the last time he used
it, 'cause it's still the non-Jew's vessel, right there on the lip.
And as he's pouring the wine, his wine, it gets mixed up
with the אסור *assur* wine before it gets into the airspace. Okay?
So in that scenario, all right, if you paid the money upfront,
then he owns it before it becomes a problem. But if he
didn't pay the money upfront, even if משיכה meshicha, *meshicha* works and
כלי *kli* works and הגבהה *hagbaah* works, and all those things work,
here it's a problem because the קנין *kinyan* only happens when it
hits the airspace, and a second before it hits the airspace, it's
mixing with forbidden wine. Okay? So that's why רב *Rav* wants you
to pay the money upfront, because money definitely works according to רב
*Rav*, and but even if משיכה meshicha *meshicha* also works, there's not
a moment, here it becomes forbidden before the משיכה meshicha *meshicha* takes
place, okay, and before the כלי *kli* takes place. Okay, so now
the גמרא *Gemara*
says, וכמאן *u'keman*, okay, good. We got all that, but one minute.
Why is this a problem? Because here, you're not selling him his
drops of wine, you're selling him your wine. So let's say I
poured my, my, you know, gallon of wine into his vessel, and
there was tiny, tiny drops of יין נסך *yayin nesech* from his
vessel that weren't
בטל *battel*, okay, point zero zero zero one percent. So it's not
בטל *battel*, okay. Even if the wine is now אסור *asur* because
of a תערובת *ta'aroves*, there's a mixture of יין נסך *yayin nesech*
there, the only thing that's forbidden in that mixture are the tiny
drops of wine. Why can't I get him to pay me for
my wine which is מותר *muttar*? It's true you can't drink any
of it because it all has tiny little drops of יין נסך
*yayin nesech*, but I'm not getting הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah* from those drops.
He's not paying me for those drops, he's paying me for my
wine. So this actually is a debate of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
*Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* and the חכמים *Chachamim*. When you have a
mixture of יין נסך *yayin nesech* and מותר *muttar* wine, okay, and
it's אסור במשהו *asur b'mashehu* in the whole thing, are you allowed
to sell it to a non-Jew? Like if I have ten gallons
of מותר *muttar* wine and one gallon of יין נסך *yayin nesech*
mixed up, and it's a dollar a gallon, can I sell the
whole thing to a non-Jew for ten dollars? Because I could argue
I'm not benefiting from the אסור *asur* wine, I'm just getting paid
for the מותר *muttar* wine. Or do you now look at the
whole thing as אסור *asur* wine and you can't sell any of
it, okay, for any price? So that's a debate of רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* and the חכמים *Chachamim*. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, if you're going to say this is a problem,
it means וכמאן *u'keman*, who is this going like? לא כרבן שמעון
בן גמליאל *lo k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*, not like רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*. דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל האמר ימכר כולו
לעובד כוכבים חוץ מדמי יין נסך שבו *de'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel ha'amar
yimacher kulo l'oved kochavim chutz mid'mai yayin nesech shebo*, that even in
a forbidden mixture you can sell it and get paid for the
היתר *heter* wine. So if that's true, this shouldn't be a problem,
because yes, the whole mixture is forbidden, but he could still pay
you for the היתר *heter* wine. So should we conclude from this
that we don't rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel*? And the general assumption is that we rule—whenever רבן שמעון *Rabban
Shimon* gives a ruling in a משנה mishna. *Mishna*, we rule like
him. Okay, so is that the only way now to read this?
So the גמרא *Gemara* says, so the גמרא *Gemara* says, yes,
it is—yes, you're correct, it's not like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel*. But that's not a problem. Even if in general
we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*, מדי
הוא טעמא אלא לרב *midei hu ta'ama ela l'Rav*, we're trying to
explain רב *Rav*'s position. האמר רב *ha'amar Rav*, רב *Rav* says, הלכה
כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל חבית בחבית *halacha k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel chavis
b'chavis*. When do we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel*? If it's not one big uniform mixture. If I have
ten barrels of כשר *kosher* wine and one barrel of non-kosher and
I don't know which is which and they get mixed up, I
can sell it to the non-Jew and say, pay me for ten
barrels. Okay? Because then we could say, like, I'm not even really
selling him the barrel. Whichever barrel is the non-kosher one, that's the
one I didn't sell him, I sold him the rest. But when
it's all mixed up into liquid, then I can't say I'm not
selling him those three drops. They're not separated at all from the
other drops. Okay? So there you're not allowed to sell it at
all. אבל לא יין ביין *aval lo yayin b'yayin*. So yes, according
to רב *Rav*, we'll rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel* when barrels get mixed up, but when wine gets mixed
up like this case, you're not allowed to say I'm selling it
to you minus the value of the טרף *treif* wine. The whole
thing is seen as one unit. The whole thing is now forbidden
because it's a mixture, and you can't sell any of it, okay?
So that was very, very long. So now what we've done is
we've taken a statement of רב *Rav* who basically has made it
crystal clear that for him money is what finalizes the sale, and
he says when you're selling wine to a non-Jew make sure to
get paid the cash upfront, okay?
So it's sort of like that line, "In God we trust, all
others pay cash." Okay, so anyway, so make sure you get the
cash upfront, okay?
And רב *Rav* makes it very clear that cash finalizes the sale.
And what we're trying to say because we're trying to assert that
it's about משיכה meshicha, *meshichah* is that maybe cash also finalizes the
sale for רב *Rav*, but maybe משיכה meshicha *meshichah* also does it.
If משיכה meshicha *meshichah* also does it, why do you need to
pay the cash? Why does it need to take possession before he
has a chance to touch it? And the basic answer is because
we're dealing in a scenario that there're tiny little droplets of wine
at the edge, and that's why the wine becomes forbidden before he
gets a chance to take possession. And once there's a little bit
of טרף *treif* wine mixed up, you can't sell any of the
wine, okay? So that's how we try to explain that this could
work with an idea that משיכה meshicha. *meshichah* also is a form
of קנין *kinyan*, and nevertheless this becomes problematic before the משיכה meshicha
*meshichah* takes place. But the simple sense of רב *Rav* is that
it's all about כסף kesef. *kesef*, it's not about משיכה meshicha, *meshichah*.
Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* is going to move on to
other cases to try to prove which is the one that does
the קנין *kinyan*, okay? So now this says like this: מתיב *meiseiv*,
I'll ask you, הלוקח גרוטאות מן עובד כוכבים *halokeach gruta'os min oved
kochavim*, you're buying scrap metal from a non-Jew, ומצא בהן עבודת כוכבים
*u'matza bahen avodas kochavim*, and amongst the scrap metal you find some
discarded little metal idols, okay, which is אסור בהנאה *asur b'hana'ah*. עד
שלא נתן מעות משך *ad shelo nasan ma'os mashach*, if you did
משיכה meshicha *meshichah* before you paid the cash, יחזיר *yachzir*, then you
can return it, okay? אם משנתן מעות משך *im mishe'nasan ma'os mashach*,
if however you paid the cash and then you did the משיכה
meshicha... *meshichah*, then you already own it, so in that case יוליך
לים המלח *yolic l'yam hamelach*, you can't return the idol and get
your money back because then now you own the idol, okay, and
now if you get your money back, you'll be getting benefit, you'll
be selling an idol, okay? So now So, in that case, now
what does it sound like? It sounds like what makes the difference
is whether you've paid the cash or not, right? So if you've
paid the cash, if you haven't paid the cash you can return
it. So it sounds like if you haven't paid the cash the
sale was in final. Give back the give back the item and
deduct it from the price. But if you've paid the cash and
the sale is final, now you can't sell back give back the
item because you'd be selling it back and you'd be getting benefit.
All right, is that clear? So the key in this משנה mishna,
is have you paid the cash or not? So that makes it
sound very clear that cash is what finalizes the sale.
אי סלקא דעתך ei salka da'atach
משיכה בעובד כוכבים קונה, meshicha b'ovad kochavim koneh, now if משיכה meshikha,
actually does take possession, so in the first case where you haven't
paid the cash but you've done משיכה, meshikha. אמאי יחזיר? amai yachazir?
Why are you entitled to return it? All right, is that clear
to everybody? You took the you took the scrap metal, you haven't
paid it, and you haven't paid, and it says if you haven't
paid cash yet you can return the item. Why? Don't you already
own the item and now you're getting הנאה from a from an
idol? So the גמרא says, אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אמר אביי amar
Abaye משום דמחזי כמקח טעות. mishum d'mechzei k'mekach ta'ut. Okay, because it
looks like, what do you mean it looks like? Because it is.
It is a מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. You never intended to buy
the idol. So the yes, משיכה meshikha, could be קונה. koneh, And
the reason you're allowed to return the idol even after you did
משיכה meshikha, was because the idol was a mistake, you never intended
to take possession of the idol. Of course, the point is if
that's true then even even after you've paid the cash you should
be allowed to return the idol because you never intended to take
possession of the idol. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava
said, one minute, if what's going on here is not whether you
were קונה koneh or not but that it was a מקח טעות,
mekach ta'ut, who cares whether it's before after you paid money? אמר
רבא, amar Rava, רישא מקח
טעות סיפא לאו מקח טעות? reisha mekach ta'ut seifa lav mekach ta'ut?
The whole thing is a מקח טעות mekach ta'ut according to you
אביי. Abaye. So if you can return it after משיכה, meshikha, you
should be able to return it after משיכה meshikha and having paid
money. The whole thing is a מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. אלא אמר
רבא, ela amar Rava, okay, we'll let's go with this. רישא וסיפא
מקח טעות. reisha v'seifa mekach ta'ut. Fine, yes. The reason you can
return it is it's all a מקח טעות, mekach ta'ut, the first
case and the second case. So then why does it matter if
you've paid money or not? Not whether you've done the קנין. The
קנין you'll have done from the type of time of משיכה meshikha,
and you can return it because of מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. So
why does it matter if you paid money? Here's why it
matters: רישא דלא יהיב זוזי, reisha d'lo yahiv zuzei, in the first
case you it's מקח טעות, mekach ta'ut, yes you own all the
rest of the metal, you don't own the idol, מקח טעות, mekach
ta'ut, but because you haven't paid money you can return the idol.
לא מיתחזי כעובד כוכבים ביד ישראל. lo mitchazei k'ovad kochavim b'yad yisrael.
It doesn't look like you're selling an idol. You're giving him back
his idol and he's not giving you any money. You're just paying
him less, right? You got it? You agreed on a thousand dollars
for the scrap metal. The idol is ten dollars' worth of metal.
So in the first case you didn't pay the money, you give
back the idol, and when you get around to paying the money
you only pay nine hundred and ninety dollars. That does not look
like you sold him an idol. You just gave him back the
idol and said this wasn't part of the sale. Okay? That's if
the money hasn't been paid yet. But סיפא דייהיב זוזי, seifa d'yahiv
zuzei, in the first case you've already gave him the thousand dollars,
you're going to give him back the idol, and what are you
going to ask for? Give me back ten dollars. So in that
case you're giving him an idol and you're getting ten dollars. It
looks like you're selling him an idol.
סיפא דייהיב זוזי מיתחזי כעובד כוכבים ביד ישראל. seifa d'yahiv zuzei mitchazei
k'ovad kochavim b'yad yisrael. It's like you're selling him an idol. So
that's a very nice read of the ברייתא. He says, look, in
neither case we could say משיכה meshika קונה. You took possession of
all the metal, but in neither case did you take possession of
the idol, that was a mistake. So the only issue of whether
the money has been paid is an issue of whether returning the
idol looks like selling the idol or not. So that's the only
issue. But in terms of קנין, that all takes place from the
time of משיכה. meshika Okay, so אמר ליה, so we're still we
still haven't come to a conclusion whether it's משיכה or
כסף. kessef, אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב אשי: amar
lei Mar Kashisha brei d'Rav Chisda l'Rav Ashi: תא שמע, ta shema,
let's come and prove it from here. המוכר יינו לעובד כוכבים, hamocher
yeino l'ovad kochavim, our משנה mishna finally, you sold wine to a
non-Jew. פסק עד שלא מדד, pasak ad shelo madad, if you have
fixed the price and then he did משיכה, דמיו מותרין. damav mutarin.
Okay, he took possession before he could touch it. And so now
why is that? ואי אמרת משיכה בעובד כוכבים אינו קונה, v'ei amrat
meshicha b'ovad kochavim eino koneh, now if משיכה doesn't work, okay, why
is that okay? He hasn't paid the money yet and he'll handle
it before he's paid the money and he'll make it forbidden. So
אמאי דמיו מותרין? amai damav mutarin? So אמר, no, הכא במאי עסקינן
דאקדים ליה דינר. hacha b'mai askinan d'akdim lei dinar. So of course
that's a very hard read of the משנה. Mishna. And the case
is basically he prepaid for the wine. In our משנה, Mishna? the
guy we're already talking that he gave the money. Okay? So then
it's very bizarre. If he gave the money, who cares whether you
were פסק pasak or not not פסק. pasak. So the point is
like this: even although he gave the money, he didn't finalize the
sale until you told him how much the price was. Here's ten
dollars. How much does it a little bizarre, you paid the money
before you even heard how much the price was. I guess so.
Maybe. But still you haven't heard the price. So although our משנה
Mishna seems to make it clear that the key is מדד, madad,
once the price is fixed it's the
משיכה... De-emphasizing the מדד madad and what we're actually sort of saying,
emphasizing, is money has been paid, that's what's going to finalize the
sale, that'll finalize the sale once the price gets fixed. So if
basically he took possession of it, that's not the קנין משיכה. kinyan
meshikha. The קנין is money before the price was fixed. Then he
had an opportunity to handle it before before the sale was finalized,
that's a problem. But if he if the price was fixed and
then he took possession, so then the sale was final before he
had a chance to handle it. The finalizing of the sale was
not the מדד, madad, the finalizing of the sale was the money
that had been prepaid.
Okay, so הכא במאי עסקינן דאקדים ליה דינר. hacha bemai askinan de-akdim
lei dinar. So the גמרא says אי הכי ei hachi if that's
true, אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end of the
משנה. Mishna מדד
עד שלא פסק דמיו אסורין madad ad she-lo pasak damav asurin if
it was measured before the price was fixed, it's forbidden. ואי דאקדים
ליה דינר ve-ei de-akdim lei dinar I've already given you the answer
to this, אמאי דמיו אסורין amai damav asurin if it was prepaid,
why is it in any case a problem in the משנה? Mishna
So the answer is because even though it was prepaid, the sale
isn't final until you know the price. אמר ליה which is what
he says back, ולדידך דאמרת משיכה בעובד כוכבים קונה. u-le-didakh de-amrat meshikha
be-oved kokhavim koneh. So he said that according to you, you read
the משנה Mishna that מדד madad is the קנין, מדד madad is
משיכה, so אמאי רישא דמיו מותרין וסיפא דמיו אסורין amai reisha damav
mutarin ve-seifa damav asurin again what's the difference about the רישא reisha
and the סיפא? seifa? In both cases he did משיכה. So clearly
somehow the idea of fixing a price interacts with the מעשה קנין.
ma'aseh kinyan. Whether the מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan is משיכה, whether the
מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan is כסף, kessef neither מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan
is final until you know the price. Okay, so even if you
read the משנה Mishna that מדידה medida is the מעשה קנין, ma'aseh
kinyan, why does it need פסק? pasak? Because פסק pasak fixing the
price is a necessary for the מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan to finalize
the sale. So אמאי רישא דמיו מותרין וסיפא דמיו אסורין? amai reisha
damav mutarin ve-seifa damav asurin? אלא מאי אית לך למימר ela mai
it lakh lemeimar what do you say? פסק סמכא דעתיה pasak samkha
dateih once the price is fixed, then he has then
he finalizes his intent to purchase it. Okay, לא פסק לא סמכא
דעתיה lo pasak lo samkha dateih before the price is fixed, even
though you did a משיכה, the sale isn't final because what?
You have to have that according to this explanation you need to
do both פסק pasak and מדד madad to be...
Right, well that is what the פשט pshat in the משנה Mishna.
is. The משנה Mishna. says in both cases you were מדד. madad.
When it's with פסק pasak the sale is final, when it's not
yet פסק pasak the sale isn't final.
But if you explain that משיכה קונה then then the role that
מדד madad plays in the whole process makes sense because מדד madad
is the מעשה קנין. ma'aseh kinyan. Right, but if according to the
דינר dinar explanation you have to say that for גמירות דעת, gmirot
da'at, it makes sense but גמירות דעת gmirot da'at requires פסק pasak
and מדד madad and then you complete the purchase.
No, no, no, no. No, it requires no, if you read it
that the קנין is done through the pre-paying of the money plus
the פסק, pasak, the reason מדד madad is mentioned is not for
the מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan but at what stage does a non-Jew
have access? Okay, if it was פסק pasak then it was final
and then it's מדד madad so he got access after it was
final. But if it was מדד madad and then it was פסק,
pasak, he got access before it was final. So the so whether
how you read מדד madad in the משנה depends on these two
reads. If it's משיכה, מדד madad is the מעשה קנין. ma'aseh kinyan.
If it's כסף kessef which hasn't been stated, מדד madad is the
moment of access. Okay. So he says, so לדידי נמי, le-didi nami,
so wait a minute, נמי אף על גב דאקדים ליה דינר פסק
סמכא דעתיה לא פסק לא סמכא דעתיה. nami af al gav de-akdim
lei dinar pasak samkha dateih lo pasak lo samkha dateih. He says
I don't have any problem explaining the משנה. The מעשה קנין ma'aseh
kinyan is either כסף kessef, which wasn't mentioned, which is bizarre that
it's not mentioned, okay, or it's מדד. madad. But either way, the
what finalizes it
is the פסק. pasak. And that's how to read the משנה. If
the פסק pasak happened before he had access you're good, if the
פסק pasak happened after he had access you're not good. Okay, so
I guess
all right, let's read one more line, then we'll be done in
here. So we'll read one more line. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי,
amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear.
I'll try to prove it from here. דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן בן נח נהרג על פחות משוה פרוטה ולא ניתן
להשבון. de-amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Noach neherag
al pachot mi-shve perutah ve-lo nitan le-hishavon. If a בן נח ben
Noach steals less than a פרוטה, perutah, that's considered גניבה, gneiva, and
he'd be נהרג neherag because any of the שבע מצות בני נח
sheva mitzvos bnei Noach they're executed for. Okay, and there's no it
doesn't make sense to return it because the Jew would be מוחל
mochel on it, it's less than a פרוטה, perutah, that's not money
that gets returned in Jewish court, but nevertheless it's considered גניבה gneiva
or גזילה gzeila for non-Jews. Now what does that have to do
with anything? ואי אמרת משיכה בעובד כוכבים אינו קונה, ve-ei amrat meshikha
be-oved kokhavim eino koneh, now if משיכה isn't קונה, אמאי נהרג? amai
neherag? Why is he נהרג? neherag? Now what type of question is
that? What do you mean why is he נהרג? neherag? So רש״י
Rashi explains it the following way, because if any you ever learned
הלכות גניבה או גזילה, hilchos gneiva o gzeila, the act of גניבה
gneiva and גזילה gzeila is only completed when a מעשה קנין ma'aseh
kinyan is done, הגבהה, a משיכה, and so on. So here we
have a scenario where if you say the only thing that's קונה
for a non-Jew is כסף, kessef well there's no כסף kessef, when
you're stealing it. Okay, but that raises other questions. How can you
give a gift to a non-Jew if you need כסף, kessef? right,
if you always need כסף? kessef So תוספות actually disagrees. תוספות says
you only need כסף kesef. in a monetary in a purchase. Okay,
in cases like a gift or in cases like theft, it would
just be You everybody would agree you wouldn't need כסף. kesef, But
let's go for רש"י right now. So for רש"י, the question is:
it's not a מעשה גניבה. maaseh g'neiva. There was no מעשה קנין,
maaseh kinyan, and מעשה גניבה maaseh g'neiva means a מעשה קנין. maaseh
kinyan. And since non-Jews it always needs money, there was no מעשה
קנין, maaseh kinyan, so why is he נהרג? neherag? Okay? He never
really stole it. So the answer is: משום דצער ליה לישראל. mishum
d'tzari lei l'Yisrael. No, even if he technically didn't steal it, he
did enough by keeping it out of the possession of the Jew,
and he caused the Jew's anguish. I don't have access to my
car. I don't care whether technically you say you've managed to keep
it away from me because, oh, well I didn't do a מעשה
קנין maaseh kinyan yet. Okay, I mean you could imagine cases, right?
We have cases like that. I could lock you out of your
house and prevent you from getting in, and technically I didn't do
a גניבה, g'neiva, I didn't take possession of the object, I didn't
do a מעשה קנין. maaseh kinyan. So it says, you know what?
Fine. Maybe it wasn't a מעשה קנין, maaseh kinyan, but it's enough
of a גניבה g'neiva by keeping the object away that it's considered
גניבה גזילה g'neiva g'zeila and it still is a transgression of בני
נח. b'nei Noach. The גמרא says: ומאי לא ניתן להישבון? u'mai lo
nitan l'hishavon? So what does it mean it can't be returned? דאינו
בתורת הישבון, d'eino b'torat hishavon, that it's not in the פרשה parsha
of being returned because it's less than a פרוטה, prutah, but really,
it never left the possession of the Jew because there was no
מעשה קנין maaseh kinyan ever done to it. אי הכי iy hachi
says the גמרא, if that's true, אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look
at the end of that. בא חבירו ונטלה ממנו, ba chaveiro v'natla
mimenu, let's say non-Jew number two stole it from non-Jew number one,
נהרג עליו. neherag alav. He didn't, and now he also did an
act of גניבה גזילה g'neiva g'zeila and he also gets executed. But
that means that non-Jew number one took possession. You with me? Because
otherwise he wouldn't be stealing from non-Jew number one. בשלמא רישא משום
דצער ליה לישראל, bishlama reisha mishum d'tzari l'Yisrael, so in the first
case I understand, you kept non-Jew number one kept it away from
the Jew, that's enough of an act of גניבה. g'neiva. But אלא
סיפא מאי עביד? ela seifa mai avid? But in the second case,
non-Jew number two didn't hurt Jew, he only hurt non-Jew number one.
So what did non-Jew number two do? It's not a גניבה, g'neiva,
he didn't hurt the Jew's access. So אלא שמע מינה משיכה בעובד
כוכבים קונה. ela shma mina meshika b'oved kochavim koneh. If the it
makes it clear that non-Jew number one through his גניבה g'neiva took
possession of it, and non-Jew number two now stole it from non-Jew
number one, so you see that משיכה works? שמע מינה. shma mina.
So that actually seems to be the conclusion of the גמרא. Of
course the problem is, is that really only proved it in a
case where it was not transactional to begin with? Right? And תוספות
says just because we agree that a non-Jew could take possession by
a מתנה matana or by גניבה גזילה g'neiva g'zeila without כסף, kesef.
it doesn't mean that in an act of transaction it wouldn't need
כסף. But anyway the גמרא seems to conclude at least for here
that משיכה's what works for a non-Jew.
Okay, and that has to be...